בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is קי"ח, Kuf Yud Chet,
technically the second to last דף daf of the גמרא, Gemara, but
we will see if we make it the last of the בבא
מציעא. Bava Metzia. We pick up with some משנה Mishna on the
bottom of קי"ז עמוד ב', Kuf Yud Zayin Amud Bet, continuing with
issues about a house and an upper level and divisions, and if
something breaks whose responsibility it is and so on, and here's what
the משנה Mishna says:
וכן בית הבד, v'chen Beit Habad, if you had a place of
like of a pressing house for olives, שהיה בנוי בסלע, shehaya banui
b'sela, which is built into a cliff, וגינה אחת על גביו, v'gina
achas al gabav, and let's say above the roof as opposed to
you had a second story, you had a house above a house,
here you had a you had an actual garden or an orchard
above a בית הבד, Beit Habad, you know an olive press,
presumably that must have been a real case, they wouldn't have made
that up. Okay, so you can imagine, right, if you have a
I'll make
a sketch of this for the class.
Totally. Anyway, you imagine like you know here's your cliff or whatever,
right, so here you know you've got your opening to your בית
הבד Beit Habad and I guess whatever I guess you have to
imagine like yeah let's say you have like that, okay, and it's
built here in the mountain and somebody here's got their orchard or
their or whatever they've got planted there. Okay, so בית Beit which
is dirt that basically is sitting on top of the roof of
your בית הבד. Beit Habad.
I'll put one olive in the בית הבד Beit Habad so that
they know.
I'll make them black. Okay, anyway, alright, so וגינה אחת על גביו
ונפחת v'gina achas al gabav v'nifchas
and the roof fell in. הרי בעל הגינה יורד וזורע למטה, harei
Ba'al hagina yored v'zorea lemata, so you can say fine you know
now again the question important question here is are we back to
a case of שוכר ומשכיר socher u'mashkir which is how the גמרא
Gemara understood this before,
or that it's the responsibility of the guy in the bottom to
fix what's on top, to fix the you know his roof the
other guy's floor if he's the if he's the landlord? Or is
this even a case where they just own it separately and
the if they own it separately it's unclear why it should be
the responsibility of the guy at the bottom and not the guy
at the top? So it seems like we're back to a case
of שוכר ומשכיר, socher u'mashkir, although there's some discussion in רש"י ותוספות
Rashi and Tosafot about that. Okay, so the guy on the top
I don't
know so the guy on the top says הרי בעל הגינה יורד
וזורע למטה harei Ba'al hagina yored v'zorea lemata עד שיעשה לבית בדו
כיפין. ad sheya'aseh l'beit bado kipin.
So the guy can go say look you have to fix my
floor and if you don't I'm going to come and plant in
the middle of your בית הבד. Beit Habad. Now of course it's
a little funny בית הבד Beit Habad doesn't necessarily a good place
for planting, it's not necessarily a reasonable solution. But there's dirt down
on the bottom. Maybe. Maybe.
And it
doesn't
have to be inside the בית הבד. Beit Habad. Well theoretically around.
Maybe maybe if there's other space below it's a good point. Okay
עד שיעשה לבית בדו כיפין ad sheya'aseh l'beit bado kipin until you
can make arches or you know like vaults for the בית הבד
Beit Habad meaning restore the roof. And fine, so it's really a
variation of what we said before. הכותל והאילן שנפלו לרשות הרבים hakotel
v'hailan she'naflu l'reshut harabim now a totally different case, a wall and
a tree fell into רשות הרבים reshut harabim והזיקו v'hiziku and they
damaged as they fell, פטור מלשלם patur milishalem you're exempt because presumably
you're an אונס, ones, although it would be an interesting question what
category would that be? Would that be a שור, shor, ממון המזיק?
mamon hamazik? Would that be an אש, esh, דרכו לילך ולהזיק? darko
leilech u'lehazik? Like this is like a perfect בבא קמא Bava Kamma
type of a question. Okay. Right I understand.
נתנו לו זמן לקוץ את האילן ולסתור את הכותל, nasnu lo zman
lakotzes es hailan u'lisator es hakotel,
let's say you weren't an אונס, ones, let's say they told the
you know the בית דין bet din came and told you hey
you've got a rickety wall, you've got a tree that's about to
collapse, you'd better remove it before it falls. ונפלו v'naflu and it
fell, בתוך הזמן
פטור, betoch hazman patur, if it's within the time period they gave
you to remove it then again you're exempt because then you're you're
still an אונס, ones, you're not yet negligent. לאחר הזמן חייב achar
hazman chayav afterwards you're liable. Okay so this presumably is a question
about negligence or אונס, ones, what category of נזק nezek it falls
into is a בבא קמא Bava Kamma question. מי שהיה כותלו סמוך
לגינת חבירו, mi shehaya kotlo samuch l'ginat chavero,
somebody had his wall near his friend's orchard or גינה gina could
also be like a vegetable garden, ונפל v'nafal and it fell. ואמר
לו v'amar lo now here not dealing with a מזיק mazik case,
we're just dealing with the fact that you've got your stones in
my yard and you've got to remove them. So we're really getting
very much into בבא בתרא Bava Batra territory. Somehow your stuff is
violated my yard, it's interfering with what I'm trying to do, you
have to remove this thing. Okay but it's not an active מזיק,
mazik, it's just sort of like in my way, so it's sort
of also similar you know to the idea like you've got to
fix your things so I can live in my עליה. aliya. You've
got to remove your rubble so I can get back use of
my yard. Okay, or imagine just the trees of your the leaves
of your tree fell into my yard, I want you to rake
it up. Okay, but anyway here we're dealing with rubble and rubble
there's actually a value. Well we'll see, we'll get to בבא בתרא.
Bava Batra. ואמר לו v'amar lo פנה אבניך pnei avanecha and I
say to you your wall collapsed, get your stones out of here,
you know you don't know you you know you might have been
an אונס ones when it collapsed, you weren't given warning etc., might
be that case that you're not חייב chayav for damage. But right
now your stones are getting in my way and I want to
plant, I want to use my yard. ואמר לו, V'amar lo, and
the owner says, and the guy who owns the stones says to
me, הגיעוך, Higiu'cha, you know what, just keep the stones. I don't
want to be bothered removing them, just keep them. Okay? אין שומעים
לו. Ein shomin lo. You cannot force that upon the owner of
the yard. Okay, if he doesn't want to agree with that agreement,
I say, no, I don't want your lousy stones, get rid of
them. And it's the guy's responsibility to remove them. Now, משקיבלו עליו,
mishekiblo alav, now, let's say I say fine, great, I will take
them, I will remove them and I'll take the stones, it's actually
worth a lot of money, good idea. Okay? ואמר לו, v'amar lo,
הילך את יציאתך heilech et yetziat'cha ואני אטול את שלי. v'ani etol
et sheli. Now
let's say I agreed to that arrangement and I removed all the
rubble, and now I'm selling them all off on eBay, and you
realize, oh my god, that guy's making thousands of dollars with my
rubble. You know what? Let me pay you for your expenses for
clearing it away and I'm going to take my stones back. Okay?
ואני אטול את שלי, v'ani etol et sheli, אין שומעים לו. ein
shomin lo. Nope, too late. We made an arrangement, you told me
that I could keep it and then I wouldn't have a responsibility,
you wouldn't have a responsibility, we agreed to that, I removed them,
now you cannot renege on that agreement.
Okay, it's rather obvious.
Well, okay, I mean, there's, fine, we'll see in the גמרא Gemara
what it says, right? Okay, the גמרא Gemara will deal with certain
cases which are a little less obvious. Okay, now,
fine. Now,
okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אין שומעים לו.
ein shomin lo. השוכר את הפועל Hasocher et hapoel לעשות עמו בתבן
ובקש. la'asot imo beteven uvakash.
Let's say I hired somebody to, you know, deal with me with
like the straw and the stubble. I don't know what he was
doing, he was gathering it up or something.
We spent his פרשה. parsha.
Right, exactly, that's true. ואמר לו, v'amar lo, תן לי שכרי, ten
li schari, and the guy says, hey, pay me up. ואמר לו,
v'amar lo, טול מה שעשית בשכרך, tol ma she'asita bischar'cha, you know
what, I'm a little cash poor, just take all the stubble that
you gathered, that'll be your fee. Okay? Even if it's like equivalent
value, even if it's of greater value, אין שומעים לו, ein shomin
lo, you cannot force that on him. משקיבלו עליו mishekiblo alav ואמר
לו v'amar lo הילך שכרך heilech schar'cha ואני אטול את שלי, v'ani
etol et sheli, אין שומעים לו. ein shomin lo. However, let's say
I say great idea, I will take this rubble, it's actually worth
more than you were going to pay me, fine, I'll do that.
And then afterwards you come and say, wait, wait, wait, I found
the cash, give me back my stubble. Nope, too late, you've already
paid me with the straw and the stubble and you cannot now
reverse it. Now, the חידוש chiddush here is is that why can
you not pay me לכתחילה lechatchila with something else? Don't we normally
say שוה כסף ככסף? shaveh kessef k'kessef? Why
is it true that you can't force me to accept the straw?
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, אין שומעים
לו, ein shomin lo, the last of the wide lines at the
top of the עמוד א amud aleph here. אע"ג דבכל דוכתי אית
ליה שוה כסף ככסף, af al gav d'bechol duchei it lei shaveh
kessef k'kessef,
even though normally we hold that anything of value is considered like
cash, הכא גבי פועל בל תלין שכרו כתיב, hacha gabei poel bal
talin scharo ktiv,
it says do not leave over, you know, delay his שכר, schar,
wages. מה דאתני בהדיה משמע. mai d'atni bahadei mashma.
So רש"י Rashi says that the שכר schar implies that they're actually,
it's based on, if you said I'm going to pay you X
amount of dollars, that means cash, and therefore it's implicit in the
arrangement that you are responsible to pay cash, because when you say
X dollars, that means in cash, it does not mean in equivalent.
Okay? There's a lot of תוספות Tosafot in the beginning of בבא
קמא Bava Kamma as well where the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma discusses other things that you're allowed to pay, that שוה
כסף ככסף, shaveh kessef k'kessef, and תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion,
what about repaying a loan and what about paying wages? Those are
two areas where we might not say שוה כסף ככסף. shaveh kessef
k'kessef. I gave you cash, you have to give me back cash.
If I agreed to pay you wages, it's implicitly in cash and
not something else. Okay? So this is very important from that perspective.
Okay? So now let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara,
just like this.
Fine.
Okay. נפרצה. Nifretza. Now,
by the way, I want to just, I want to read this
little תוספות Tosafot here about ואמר לו הגיעוך. v'amar lo higiu'cha. That
my wall collapsed in your yard and I said, you know what,
just keep it. I can't force you to take it. So תוספות
Tosafot says, I might not be able to force you to take
it, but why does not saying I'm מפקיר mafkir it free me
of the responsibility of cleaning it up?
So look at תוספות. Tosafot. אע"ג דמפקיר ניזקין לאחר נפילה דאונס מן
הפרק המניח דפטור, af al gav d'mafkir nizakin le'achar nefilla d'ones min
perek hamaniach d'patur, there's a classic case in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma.
I'm walking in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, all my glassware breaks in
the middle of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, falls off my donkey, it's
this public hazard. If I מפקיר mafkir it immediately before I have
a chance to clean it up, then I'm not liable. It's, its
falling wasn't my responsibility, and I only become liable for damages or
whatever if I had a time to clean and I didn't clean,
then I'm negligent. But if in that gap between when it fell
and when, before I've yet had a chance to clear it away
I was מפקיר mafkir it, so I wasn't חייב chayav for its
falling and now I'm not חייב chayav for cleaning it away because
I was מפקיר mafkir before I was negligent. So, and now it's
not mine anymore, I'm not liable for it anymore. So תוספות Tosafot
says, you know the same could be true. My wall falls into
your yard, makes a big mess. If I מפקיר mafkir it right
away, it's not my responsibility to clean it up. I wasn't negligent
that it fell into your wall, and I wasn't negligent that I
didn't clear it away because I was מפקיר mafkir immediately. So technically
that would be correct, but here the guy wasn't מפקיר mafkir immediately.
Even even though I'm saying to the guy take it away, you
know, you can keep it, you clean it away, you keep it,
תוספות Tosfos says right, הכא תוספות תוספות אשתמוטי קמשתמיט ואינו מפקיר כדאמרי
בגמרא. hacha Tosfos Tosfos ishamutei kamishtamei ve'eino mafkir k'd'amri bigmara. I'm really
just trying to avoid cleaning it up myself. I'm not really being
מפקיר. mafkir. Okay, so if I was really מפקיר mafkir though, I
would be exempt even though my wall collapsed in your house if
I was מפקיר mafkir right away. So that's important to remember that
הלכה. halacha. Yes?
These two cases one is a private space and one is a
public space, does that matter?
Well, if even in a public domain my broken shards of glass
are not my responsibility, how much more so are they not my
responsibility if they fell into your yard? Right?
What if it was the other way?
Well, the right, so it might be the other way would be
more, but that was like a קל וחומר kal vachomer argument. Okay,
so now the גמרא gemara first deals with the case about the
garden on top of the pressing floor, which is really like a
parallel to the case before about the second about the attic on
top of the, not the attic, the second story on top of
the house,
where if he doesn't fix it you can go and live with
the guy below. נפחתה. nifchasa. So how much does the floor have
to have to like break open?
רב אמר ברובה ושמואל אמר בארבע. Rav amar beruba u'shmuel amar bearba.
Rav says only when the majority of the floor, and Shmuel says
in ארבע טפחים. arba tefachim. Four, actually here it's ארבע, arba, before
it was ארבעה. arba'ah. Before it was four טפחים, tefachim, here it's
ארבע, arba, which would be
ארבע אמות. arba amot.
It's interesting, I don't know if anybody's noticed that difference. I haven't
checked the הלכה, halacha, but before it said four טפחים. tefachim. They
say ארבע טפחים.
arba tefachim.
Yeah, but before it said ארבעה. arba'ah. So do they switch the
גירסא girsa there, or they still have it as ארבע? arba?
ארבע arba with an עין. ayin.
Just without a ה. hei. Interesting. Before it was ארבעה, arba'ah, which
is טפחים. tefachim. Anyway, רב אמר ברובה אבל ארבע אמות זורע חציו
למטה וחציו למעלה. Rav amar beruba aval arba amot zorei'ach chetzvo l'mata
vechetzvo l'ma'ala.
Certainly you have to give the guy place to plant, but he
doesn't get to move the whole operation downstairs, okay? If it's just
a small space, he can do some of it above and some
of it below. Only when it's the majority does he move the
whole operation downstairs. ושמואל אמר בארבע. u'shmuel amar bearba. Four, no, four
טפחים tefachim is enough to move the whole operation downstairs. אין אדם
זורע חציו למטה וחציו למעלה. ein adam zorei'ach chetzvo l'mata vechetzvo l'ma'ala.
You can't ask him to do half above, half below. וצריכא, utzricha,
now this is exactly what they debated before by the case of
the second story. But you need to tell me both cases. דאישמעינן
בדירה, di'ashme'inan b'di'ira, if you told me the case of a domicile,
בהא קאמר שמואל, behach kama shmuel, that's where Shmuel says you know
four טפחים tefachim is enough, a good enough reason to move the
whole thing downstairs. משום דלא עביד איניש דדייר פורתא הכא פורתא הכא.
mishum delo avid inish de'dayir portsa hacha portsa hacha. People don't split
their living quarters. I'm doing most of my stuff up here but
when I need to go to my closet or my dresser or
my easy chair, I'll go downstairs. Okay. So in that case you
don't say it. פורתא הכא פורתא הכא. portsa hacha portsa hacha. אבל
לענין זריעה, aval l'inyan zri'ah, but when it comes to planting your
field, עביד איניש דחזר הכא פורתא והכא פורתא. avid inish deshazar hacha
portsa vehacha portsa. Yes, fields aren't always contiguous. Sometimes you have a
portion of your field somewhere else, so that would not be crazy
to ask the guy to do downstairs. So maybe Shmuel would agree
to that case. אימא מודי ליה לרב, eima modei lei l'rav, maybe
he would agree to Rav. ואימר בהא, ve'imar behacha, and just had
given you the case of the planting, בהא קאמר רב, behach kama
rav, that's where Rav says that it's okay to do half above
and half below. I'm sorry, right. אבל בהא, aval behach,
but in the case of the domicile, אימא מודי ליה לשמואל, eima
modei lei l'shmuel, maybe he would agree that even a small space
it's unreasonable to ask him and even a small space maybe he'd
agree to Shmuel that he can move the whole thing downstairs. צריכא.
tzricha. So you have to tell me whether it's a domicile where
it's pretty unreasonable to split it up, or whether it's a garden
or whatever an orchard where it's, where it's not as unreasonable. Either
way Rav holds in both cases it only you only get to
move downstairs when there's the majority is destroyed and Shmuel says even
a small space.
Okay. נפלו זמנו. naflo zmaino. Let's say they gave him time to
clear away the wall or the tree. So he has to do
it within the time,
but if it falls within the time he's not liable. וכמה זמן
בית דין? vechama zman beis din? What's the standard amount of time
בית דין beis din gives somebody to do something like this? אמר
רבי יוחנן שלשים יום. amar rabbi yochanan shloshim yom. Thirty days. Now
this is a little, this is interesting, because if you take a
look at תוספות, Tosfos, זמן בית דין שלשים יום. zman beis din
shloshim yom. תוספות Tosfos says ומכאן אנו למדים זמן בית דין לפרוע
חוב ולכמה דברים דהוי שלשים יום.
umikan anu l'meidim zman beis din lifro'a
chov u'lkama devarim de'havei shloshim yom. Here's where we learned that based
on this גמרא, gemara, I mean where does the גמרא gemara know
it from, I don't know, but the standard time that בית דין
beis din gives to get things done is thirty days. Okay? So
somebody is like you know standard time to pay back a loan
is thirty days. Standard other types of things as well. Now of
course you might think it might matter right? Like if a loan
is you know, I mean it's one thing if something is about
to imminently cause damage or might soon cause a public hazard, it's
another type of a thing I borrow money, maybe often when I
borrow money I need them for a longer period, it's not about
בית דין, beis din, it's about how long do people normally need
loans for? Right? Now there's another idea of שלשים יום shloshim yom
though which is not when do I pay back the loan, but
how long do I have to be in arrears before בית דין
beis din does something about it? That we saw before. That's a
different story. That's not how long of you know what's my normal
assumption of my lending borrowing period, but when am I sort of
in violation, when does בית דין beis din put me on notice
and if I'm not acting on it within a period of time
they're going to act. So that's the next thing תוספות Tosfos says
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel רבן גמליאל נמי דאמר לעיל אף אתה לא
ימכרו עד שלשים יום Rabban Gamliel nami d'amar l'eil, af atah lo
yimachru ad shloshim yom says, you know, this idea of returning the
collateral once the guy's in arrears, after thirty days we sell off
the collateral. He says that's a similar idea. בית דין Beis Din
put you on notice, you didn't act, within thirty days we take
action. Okay, but then תוספות Tosafos says another point, ומיהו לכל הניזקין
לא אמר שיזמן שלשים יום. umihu l'chol hanizikin lo amar sheyizman shloshim
yom. It's not that anytime something I have might cause damage I've
got thirty days to do it. It might very well depend on
the degree of risk, you know, that's involved. Okay, כמו הכא דהא
לעיל גבי נשברה כדו ולא סילקה נפלה גמלו ולא העמידה רבי מאיר
מחייב בהיזיקא ואין זמן בית דין שלשים יום. k'mo hacha deha l'eil
gabi nishbera kado v'lo silka nafla gamlo v'lo he'emida Rabi Meir mechayev
b'hizika v'ein zman Beis Din shloshim yom. Let's say my bottle breaks
in the middle of רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim. I say, yeah, I'll
clean it up within thirty days. Okay? So obviously some things the
idea is you got to do it immediately. But other things where
it's not immediately causing a hazard, okay, בית דין Beis Din gives
me thirty days to take care of things. So that's interesting that
תוספות Tosafos sort of pulls together a couple of diverse things about
that.
והאידנא, v'idana, thirty days today is the standard. Really? Is that thirty
days to return something if you buy it in a store?
Oh, that's a good point, right. Yeah, you're right, that's a good
point.
Thirty days return policy, okay, unless you go by Zappos or L.L.
Bean and then you have it for life. Okay, מאי איכא למימר,
mai ika l'meimar, now back to continuing, if your wall is near
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, excuse me, if your wall sort of fell
and then the question is cleaning it up, okay, and you tell
the guy, just keep it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, המדקתני
סיפא hamidkatni seifa from the end of it it says, הילך יציאותיך,
heilach yetziosecha, if I say to you, look, look, look,
here's the expense for cleaning it, give me back all of my
rubble, it says you don't listen to me. מכלל דפנויי עסקינן, michlal
d'pinuyei askinan, it sounds like at what stage do you now, you,
if yours is the field that the rubble, the wall fell into,
at what stage are you קונה kona the rubble? Is it irreversible
once you clean it up? Because the משנה Mishnah says I can't
say to you I'll pay you for your expenses, give it back
to me. So it sounds like once you clean it up, you
take possession of it. So the גמרא Gemara says, why don't you
take possession earlier? אמאי, amai, as soon as you agree and say
yes, great idea, then it's in your field, you should be קונה
kona it immediately. That should be the point of no return. Why
is your cleaning it up the point of no return? So טעמא
דפנויי, taama d'pinuyei, the reason is you cleaned it up. הלא פנויי,
halo pinuyei, if you didn't clean it up, לא, lo, I would
still be able to get it back. אמאי, amai, why? דתקני ליה
שדיה, d'tikni lei sadei, let the field take possession of it. דאמר
רבי יאשיה בר רבי חנינא חצר של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו.
d'amar Rabi Yoshiya bar Rabi Chanina chatzer shel adam kona lo shelo
mida'ato. A person's yard takes possession for him even without his awareness.
Now the question is why do we have to say שלא מדעתו?
shelo mida'ato? This is מדעתו. mida'ato. So תוספות Tosafos says, well, there's
also a question here about whether the guy is present in his
field. You might remember there was earlier discussions whether חצר chatzer works
whether you have to be standing next to your field or not
next to your field. So תוספות Tosafos sort of without getting into
the details says maybe that's why we reference this idea to say
you don't even always need to be standing there, even sometimes שלא
מדעתו. shelo mida'ato. So why here did you have to clear it
away? So the גמרא Gemara says, הני מילי היכא דקא מכוין לאקנויי
ליה.
hani mili heicha d'ka mechavein
l'aknoyei lei. You know what, that's
true. If I really intended to give it to you, here, just
take the rubble, clear it off, if I was really serious, then
you would be קונה koneh as soon as you said yes. לאקנויי
ליה. l'aknoyei lei.
אבל הכא אחמויי אשיינך דקא משתמיט ליה. aval hacha achmuyei ashaynach d'ka
mishtamit lei. Here, I'm not really trying to give it to you.
I'm just trying to stop you from אחמויי אשיינך. achmuyei ashaynach. I'm
trying to stop you from bothering me that hey, go clean up
your thing. Oh, yeah, just keep it. So therefore, the only, if
it gets to the point where you actually clear it away, then
I can't say I was just pushing you off and not being
serious. You're actually investing the work to clear it away and I
said, you know what, don't bother me with it, you keep it.
So at that point, we have to say that I really was
implicitly agreeing to give it to you. But before you've done the
work, well, that's a good question, Mike, why don't we say if
you're doing half of the work, right, why don't we say when
you start the work? That's an interesting question because that shows that
you really have agreed to it and are serious about it. I
don't know, that's a good question. Okay, but at least the גמרא's
Gemara point is that prior, so it is a good question why
do you have to do the whole work, but at least the
גמרא's Gemara point is that prior to doing the work, we could
say that I wasn't really serious that I wanted to give it
to you, I was just trying to get out of having to
deal with it. Okay, now we move on, השוכר את הפועל בבתבן.
hasocher es hapoel batseven. If you're sort of gathering up the straw
and I say just keep the straw, don't ask me for wages,
I can't force that on you, but once you said yes, then
I can't renege on it. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
וצריכא. utzricha. Now, דאי אשמעינן להך
קמייתא. d'ei ashmi'inan l'hach kamaisa. Now, you have to give me both
cases: one about the rubble that I'm locked in once you clear
it away and one about the straw. Now obviously one point that
you have to say both cases for the reason we just saw,
that the rubble thing isn't binding immediately when you agree upon it,
it's only binding once you start clearing it away or once you
finish clearing it away. But the גמרא Gemara says there's something else
also we learn from the both cases, the rubble case and the
סיפא seifa case, the case where I'm giving you the straw as
the fee. Also as רש"י Rashi tells us what we learn from
the case of the straw as the fee is that I can't
pay you wages in cash equivalent, I have to pay you wages
in actual cash. Okay, so there's a lot of things you learn
from each case, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. וצריכא,
utzricha, you need both. דאי אשמעינן להך קמייתא d'ei ashmi'inan l'hach kamaisa
the first one. הגיעך, higi’ach, אין שומעין לו ain shom’in lo משום
דלית ליה אגרא גביה. mishum deleis lei agra gabei.
When in the first case when I say, I say look just
keep the rubble, that I can't force it on you. Why can't
I force it on you? Because because I don't owe you any
money. Okay, so therefore it's not like it's in payment of any
debt, so it's not like that automatically now is binding and counts.
משום דלית ליה אגרא גביה. mishum deleis lei agra gabei. אבל הכא,
Aval hacha, דאית ליה אגרא גביה, de’is lei agra gabei, here where
I owe you money, אימא שומעין לו. eima shom’in lo. Maybe I
would say that I can force you to take this. Meaning it's
funny, on one hand I owe you more, but on the other
hand this is payment of a debt and maybe cash equivalent should
count. Essentially this is what רש"י Rashi said, דהוה אמינא de’hava amina
שווה כסף
ככסף. shava kesef k’kesef. I owe you money and this is equivalent
and let this count. דאמרי אינשי, D’amri inshi, people say,
ממארי רשותך פארי אפרע. mimarei reshusach parei efra. From the person you
owe money to, you should
even be willing to accept like you know like סובין, subin, like
what's it, סובין, subin, yeah fodder or something. You
know you get what you need, whatever you can get.
Exactly, you know you should be willing to take junk from the
person who owes you money. So I might think, it's funny the
גמרא Gemara quotes that rather than the principle of שווה כסף ככסף.
shava kesef k’kesef. But the point is fine, I owe you money,
this is cash equivalent, maybe I should be able to pay you.
So that would be a good הוה אמינא. hava amina. So it
has to tell you no, that you can't pay your workers in
cash equivalent, you have to pay them in cash. ואי אשמעינן הכא,
V’ei ashmeinan hacha, הכא הוא דאין
שומעין לו, hacha hu de’ain shom’in lo, it's just told me here
in this case that payment you can't just force him to take
the the straw, I might say here you can't but in the
case of rubble you can. Why? הכא
דמשקבל
עליו אין שומעין לו
Hacha demishe’kibel alav
ain shom’in lo משום דאית ליה אגרא גביה. mishum de’is lei agra
gabei. So again, because here there's already the structure that I owe
you money, there would be a הוה אמינא hava amina first of
all that I could pay you in in סובין, subin, that I
could pay you in straw. So it has to tell me that
even here I can't pay you in straw. But it also here
you might say that because I owe you money once you agree
to it I can't back out. Whereas in the case where the
wall falls into your רשות, reshus, A, it's less likely that I
would be able to force it onto you, and it's also less
likely that you would be that we'd get to a point of
no return because fundamentally there's not that pre-existing structure. Fundamentally I don't
owe you money. So משום דאית ליה אגרא גביה. mishum de’is lei
agra gabei. אבל הכא דלית ליה אגרא
גביה, Aval hacha deleis lei agra gabei, by the case of the
wall collapsing where I don't owe you any money, אימא שומעין לו,
eima shom’in lo, maybe I could always be able to back out?
צריכא. Tzricha. So it's actually interesting, it's saying both of the cases,
you need to tell me both cases because there's two stages here.
One is I can't force it onto you, and the other is
once you agree you can't back out. And I might have thought
that in the case of your fee would be more of a
reason to think I could force it onto you because I already
owe you money and this is just an equivalent. On the other
hand the הלכה halacha that you can't back out, okay, I would
have thought that here in the case of the fee, you know,
there's more reason to say you can't back out, whereas in the
other case maybe you could always back out. All right, but again
because there's not that pre-existing structure. Why would they back out?
In the end of the case even in the case even here
I can't force it onto you and even in the other case
where I can't back out, even though there's no once you actually
have cleared it away, even though there's no pre-existing structure. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אין שומעין לו. ain shom’in
lo. So in this case about forcing you to accept the you
know the straw as your fee, you don't listen to me. והתניא,
Ve’hatanya, but we have a ברייתא Braisa that says שומעין לו, shom’in
lo, I can force you to accept it. So how do you
reconcile this? אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא, Amar Rav Nachman lo kashya,
it's not difficult. כאן בשלו כאן בשל חבירו. Kan b’shelo kan b’shel
chaveiro. It matters whether I am having you do work in my
field or my friend's field. Now this is a little funny. In
my field I can't force you to accept the straw. But if
you're working at my friend's field, I agreed to pay you for
your work in my friend's field, I can force you to accept
the straw. Now that's bizarre because maybe the גמרא Gemara apparently thinks
that if I'm telling you to work in my friend's field I
have less of a responsibility.
And then your friend didn't ask you?
Well, that's very unclear. Right. So let's just hold off a second.
I have less of a responsibility to pay you directly, maybe my
friend has more of the responsibility, and therefore because I have less
of the responsibility I can pay you even in a cash equivalent.
That might be, but how can I pay you in my friend's
straw? It's not my straw to give you. So it's a very
strange הוה אמינא. hava amina.
The point is though if the worker has a טענה taina after
getting paid in kind, he has to work it out with the
friend.
Yeah, but still right. But the still question is that אמר ליה
רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l’Rav Nachman, Rava said to Rav
Nachman,
בשלו מאי טעמא, b’shelo mai ta’ama, why can you not pay him
if he's working in your field with the straw? משום דאמר ליה
אגראי עליך, mishum de’amar lei agrai alach, because we say you have
the responsibility to pay and you have to pay in cash. בשל
חבירו נמי אגראי עליך. B’shel chaveiro nami agrai alach. In your friend's
field as well, if you asked him to work in your friend's
field, that's your responsibility to pay. דתניא, Detanya, השוכר את הפועל Hasocher
es hapo’el לעשות בשלו והראהו בשל חבירו, la’asos b’shelo ve’her’ahu b’shel chaveiro,
you said I want you to work for me but instead you
pointed out your friend's field, but he thought he was working for
you, נותן לו שכרו משלו, nosin lo scharo mishelo, you have to
pay him the full amount. וחוזר ונוטל מבעל הבית מה שנהנהו, V'chozer
v'notel miba'al habayis mah shehenaho, and then you go and you collect
from the
owner what you benefited him. Okay, anyway as תוספות Tosafos points out,
besides the question that it's your full responsibility to pay there, it's
bizarre. How could you pay with your friend's straw? Right, your friend
didn't agree to it. Anyway, אלא אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא כאן
בשלו כאן בשל הפקר, Ella amar Rav Nachman lo kashya kan beshelo
kan beshel hefker,
which is also strange. So if I have you work for me,
then I have responsibility to pay you. I can't pay you an
equivalent. Let's say I found a field that had all of this
was abandoned and all this straw to collect, if I hired you
to collect the straw, then you're not really working for me because
it's not really my field. So I don't really have a responsibility
to pay you. Okay, well, maybe I am trying to claim the
straw, but here's the question.
Right, so what I am trying to do is I am trying
to claim the straw, but here's the question. So here's the point.
If by your collecting the straw, הלכתית halachically it becomes my straw,
and now we're going to get into a question of מגביה מציאה
לחבירו, magbi'ah metzi'ah lachaveiro, then it turns out that you worked for
me, you benefited me, you worked for me, et cetera, and then
I have to pay you and I can't pay you in an
equivalent. But if in your collecting of the straw I wasn't קונה
koneh the straw, מגביה מציאה לחבירו לא קנה חבירו, magbi'ah metzi'ah lachaveiro
lo kanah chaveiro, then at the end of the day, you didn't
really do anything for me, and I don't really have to pay
you, but then you could just keep the straw. Right, but then
it's a funny, it's not like I can pay you what I
owe you in straw. Then it's like I never owed you anything
and you have all this straw that you can choose to keep
for yourself. So it's like a funny way of formulating the whole
issue. Also it raises interesting questions, right, which we never really got
to, which is: Can I... what is the legal construct in which
I owe you money when I actually hire you? Let's say for...
it's not exactly the same as a contract because, you know, I
can't make you a contract to agree to pay. Let's say I
wanted to tell you Michael, I will give you a hundred dollars
if you go ahead and you like run around this building, you
know, for the next three hours, right? So would I owe you
the hundred dollars? You didn't do anything for me. I mean, you
know, is that a contract? Is that a binding contract to get
you to do something and just agree to pay you?
Me, what? You're just saying just a...
Yeah. Well, אסמכתא asmachta right, and like also like maybe there's even
no, you know, there's no... right, it's like, yeah, essentially it's an
אסמכתא. asmachta. There's no binding contract there. I mean, we know שכירות.
sechirus. שכירות sechirus is I am paying you to do a service
for me. So when we... when it's a type of a שכירות,
sechirus, I obligate myself. But to just סתם stam pay you for
doing something that's not benefiting me, you know, what is that? Is
that like a contract?
The language here is שכירות. sechirus.
I understand. But the reason I'm saying it is is that if
I don't own the field and when you're picking it up I
don't own the wheat because מגביה מציאה לחבירו לא קנה חבירו, magbi'ah
metzi'ah lachaveiro lo kanah chaveiro, it sounds like fundamentally I don't owe
you anything. What do you mean I don't owe you anything? I
agreed to pay you a hundred dollars for collecting the wheat. At
the end of the day, what difference does it make if I
own the wheat or don't own the wheat? You did what I
asked you for. I agreed to pay you a certain amount of
money. But nevertheless, what emerges from this גמרא Gemara is is that
if it works out that it was not really a service for
me, I didn't get anything out of the deal, then I don't
owe you anything, even though I agreed to pay you. Okay, so
that's my point here is an important point that that all of
this assumption of שכירות sechirus when it's a type of a... when
it works within a structure, paying you to do a service for
me. When I... I just agree you to pay you to do
some... something and it's not a service, it might... there might not
be the proper structure to obligate me. So therefore if it's a
הפקר hefker field and you collect it and I don't... and I
don't wind up owning the wheat at the end, I don't owe
you anything and you just keep it yourself. But again, it's worth
noting, I don't owe you, even though I said I would pay
you. Okay, so that's a really... so that's an important idea that
you need this structure of שכירות. sechirus. That's... that idea.
Yes, that you'd never have to pay all sorts of people who
provide services for me.
Why not?
They're all שכירות. sechirus. No, no. If I just ask you to
pick up stuff in a field that's not mine, okay, that's not
a service for me. Okay, let's say I decide I hate the
fact that there's vacant lot that's here and you know, it looks
disgusting. It's... now, it doesn't hurt me or do anything to me
or whatever. I just think that as a public service we should
clean it up and I pay you twenty dollars to clean it
up. Do I have to pay you? Is that considered a service
for me? What did you do for me? Now, maybe what you
did for me was because I was my... I had a desire
to have a clean field, I don't know. But I'm saying it's...
right, it's interesting question about what constitutes שכירות. sechirus. The גמרא Gemara
assumes that if you're קונה koneh the wheat that you picked up
in this הפקר hefker field, even though I agreed to pay you
for this act, I wouldn't owe you the money. Okay, so that's
pretty interesting. Let's take a look.
It's interesting what you're saying, where do you draw the line? You
know, like... I understand. No, you saying like run around, okay, but
let's say you're a circus performer and you know, I ask you
to perform. I get something out of that.
I'm being entertained.
You're being entertained.
All right, I understand. So that's a good question. But the point
is you need a concept of שכירות, sechirus, okay, where it's not
just a... a verbal contract to pay for doing an action. It
has to be a service, okay? So let's take a look. Okay,
אלא
לא קשיא כאן בשלו כאן בשל הפקר. Ella lo kashya kan bishelo
kan beshel hefker. And therefore because it's הפקר, hefker, you don't owe
him money and therefore he's allowed to keep it. And presumably therefore
also you don't own it. So because the presumption is that if
he picks up הפקר, hefker, you don't own it, he gets... to
keep it. איתיבי רבא לרב נחמן, Eisiv Rava le-Rav Nachman, so Rava
challenged Rav Nachman: מציאת פועל לעצמו, metzi'as po'el le-atzmo, if a פועל
po'el finds something that he gets to keep it for himself. אימתי?
בזמן שאמר לו בעל הבית: נכש עמי היום, עדור עמי היום. Eimasai?
Bi-zman she-amar lo ba'al ha-bayis: nakesh imi hayom, ador imi hayom. That's
when he's being hired to do a specific task
like hoeing or whatever, weeding.
Then when he picks it up, he's not doing it in the
service of the בעל הבית, ba'al ha-bayis, so he owns it himself.
אבל אמר לו: עשה עמי מלאכה היום, Aval amar lo: asei imi
melachah hayom, if he just generically says, "Work for me today," then
מציאתו לבעל הבית. metzi'aso le-ba'al ha-bayis. Then when he finds something, he's
like an extension of the בעל הבית. ba'al ha-bayis. אפילו אם מגביה
מציאה לחברו לא קנה חברו. Afilu im magbia metzi'ah le-chavero lo kanah
chavero.
If a פועל po'el picks up something for the בעל הבית ba'al
ha-bayis in the service of the בעל הבית, ba'al ha-bayis, he does
own it. So here too, if you hired him to gather the
wheat in a field or the straw in a field of הפקר,
hefker, you the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis would own it and he
would do a service for you and you would owe him the
fee. And therefore you couldn't tell him, "Just keep the straw in
your fee."
So what's the distinction between the two cases?
One case is that he's only in your service to do a
specific task, so picking it up he's working for himself. Whereas when
he's in
your service... alright, whatever, that's a different question about why he's able
to take a work break, the גמרא Gemara says maybe he picks
it up while he was doing something else, but that's not our
issue. But if he's actually picking it up in the service of
the בעל הבית, ba'al ha-bayis, then the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis owns
it. So here too, if it's הפקר, hefker, you own it and
therefore you the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis owe him his fee and
you can't pay him in something else. Okay, אלא אמר רב נחמן,
ela amar Rav Nachman, rather Rav Nachman says, לא קשיא. כאן בהגבהה
כאן בהבטה. lo kashya. Kan be-hagbahah kan be-habatah.
We're going to still deal with a הפקר hefker field, but the
question is whether you end up owning the wheat in the הפקר
hefker field. You told him, "Watch all of this straw. I'm going
to go hire people to go collect it. It's your job to
watch it. I'll pay you ten dollars for watching it." And then
we come back and instead of paying you the ten dollars I
say, "Just keep it in the straw." So do I own it
to free it to you or not? So if basically... so let's
take a look.
הפקר hefker field. So if by watching it I own it, so
therefore I own the straw, your watching made it what's a type
of a קנין, kinyan, then again, you did something for me and
I own the straw and now I have to pay you cash,
I can't pay you in straw. But if in your watching it
you didn't own it, I don't wind up owning it, הבטה habatah
is not קונה. koneh. Okay, שאין הבטה קונה. she-ein habatah koneh.
We're going to see that.
Okay,
so in that case,
then you actually didn't do a service for me and therefore I
can have you just keep it. Now that's actually pretty funny anyway
because maybe you did a service, if you take a look at
רש״י, כאן בהגבהה כאן בהבטה. Rashi, kan be-hagbahah kan be-habatah. רש״י Rashi
says, איירי בשל הפקר, משכחת לה כששכרו ללקט תבן וקש. airi bi-shel
hefker, meshachas lah keshe-secharo le-laket teven va-kash. בהגבהה, Be-hagbahah, if he lifted
it up, דפועל, de-po'el, ועל כן שכרו עליו. ve-al ken secharo alav.
And therefore you now took possession of this for me, I own
the grain, I own the wheat, whatever it is, the straw, and
I have to pay you cash. ובברייתא כששכרו למלאכת הבטה, כגון לשמור
או להשליך מיד ליד. U-ve-vrayisa keshe-secharo le-melaches habatah, kegon lishmor o le-hashlich
mi-yad le-yad.
I asked you to do something which wasn't
actually doing a קנין, kinyan, you just were guarding the field, or
you of this הפקר hefker wheat, or you were moving it without
picking it up, okay? דליכא הגבהה, דאמר ליה: השתא לא זכי בהאי,
אנא זיל את זכי ביה. De-leika hagbahah, de-amar leh: hashta lo zachi
be-hai, ana zil at zachi beih. Then you could say, "Look, I
haven't taken possession of it yet, you haven't yet done a קנין
kinyan on it, you take possession of it." Of course what I
don't understand is, it's wonderful that I the owner don't take possession
of it yet, but why don't I owe you your fee? You
spent the whole day moving around this, or guarding, you know, this
field of straw. So I wasn't קונה koneh the straw and you
weren't קונה koneh the straw. Nobody was, you know, nobody was קונה
koneh the straw. Wonderful, but I still have to pay you, you
spent the whole day watching the field, right? So it's not clear
to me just because I don't own the straw why I... yes,
of course I can tell you keep the straw, nobody owns it,
you can keep it, but why does that get me out of
my obligation to pay you the fee I agreed upon?
We could even ask the other direction: I watched the straw all
day, right? It's הפקר. hefker. Straw, right. At the end of the
day I take the straw, put it in my house. How does
he still come and
say...
right, that is my question.
You, right, I don't own it so you can take
it, right. But why don't I owe you for it, why don't
I owe you?
You take the straw, it's not yours,
right, exactly, that's what I don't understand. Unless the point is that
since at the end of the day I don't own the straw,
we could say you didn't really do a service for me because
I don't own it yet. But I could imagine the case where
you did a service for me: you watched it until I could
get workers to come take it and gather it together, so the
service you did is you prevented other people from taking it until
now I could... so I don't really understand. I understand why I
don't own it, I don't understand why I don't have to pay
you your fee.
Why would the employer even hire the guy if
he wasn't going to plan on taking it? Exactly, he was owning
it, really. Well, it doesn't matter what you intend to own it,
halachically you might not yet own it, I mean I could imagine...
right, but I don't, so that's it, I don't understand why he
doesn't have to pay the fee. I understand why the other guy
could take the straw. Anyway, so let's take a look.
Okay, לא קשיא, lo kashya, where are we? כאן בהגבהה כאן בהבטה,
Kan be-hagbahah kan be-habatah,
just looking at it isn't קונה koneh it. And therefore in that
case, since nobody was קונה koneh it yet, you can tell him
to keep the straw. Why you don't have to pay him I
don't get, but you can tell him to keep the straw. you
can tell him to keep the straw and nobody owns it yet.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. רבא Rava says הבטה בהפקר תנאי היא. Abbata
be-hefker tanai hi.
No, actually, the question about whether just looking at הפקר hefker is
a קנין kinyan is a debate of תנאים. tannaim. Now, this is
very strange. You might remember, it's very nice that this actually goes
back to the very first מימרא meimra of בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia.
I don't know if anybody remembers this, but the very first מימרא
meimra of בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, which is I found it, the
other guy says I found it. The גמרא Gemara says והוה אמינא
ve-hava mina is that I found it, I mean I saw it
first. And is is הבטה בהפקר קונה? Abbata be-hefker koneh? And the
גמרא Gemara said there it wasn't. Now, how here could הבטה בהפקר
Abbata be-hefker be קונה? koneh? So רש"י Rashi makes a point of
saying that הבטה Abbata here is, you know, כגון, kegon, you know,
it's like
it's that you're watching it and protecting it. And maybe that aspect
of watching and protecting is seen as a type some type of
a קנין kinyan with הפקר. hefker. Okay, not just סתם stam looking.
Let's take a look. So he says that's actually a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. תנן, Tenan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah. שומרי ספיחי
שביעית נוטלין שכרן מתרומת הלשכה. Shomrei sefichi shevi'is notlin secharan mi-terumas ha-lishkah.
People are watching stuff, wild stuff that grows on שביעית Shevi'is for
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because they want to bring from it
from the grain עומר ושתי הלחם, Omer ushtei ha-lechem, which is a
קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. So these people that are watching and protecting
other people from taking it, this wild שביעית Shevi'is produce, are being
paid from the temple funds. Okay. רבי יוסי אומר הרוצה מתנדב הוא
ושומר חנם. Rabbi Yose omer harotzeh minadiv hu ve-shomer chinam. Somebody who
wants to can dedicate, devote, donate their time and watch it for
free. You don't have to pay the guy to watch it. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said back to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, אתה
אומר כן? atah omer ken? You think that that's what you can
do? אין באין משל ציבור. Ein ba'in mishel tzibbur. According to you,
it would not be a communal קרבן korban if because we're not
paying the guy to watch it. Now how does not paying the
guy to watch it make it a non-communal קרבן? korban? In the
end of the day, we're just taking this wheat or or barley
and making it into עומר. Omer. So or שתי הלחם. shetei ha-lechem.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי. mai lav behaki
mipalgi. This must be the debate. דתנא קמא סבר הבטה בהפקר קני.
De-Tanna Kamma savar Abbata be-hefker kani. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds,
look, you're going to be watching and guarding this grain. If we
don't pay you, then you're going to be קונה koneh it yourself.
Okay, you're watching it but we'll make it yours. It's like you're
exerting your control and your ownership. It'll make it yours. And then
you and then you're going to give it to us, the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It won't be a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. It'll
be a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid, it'll be coming from something that's
yours privately. ויהיב ליה אגרא, Ve-yahivlei agra, if we give you your
fee, אין, in, then it works. Then you're watching it for us
and therefore you're watching it we'll be קונה koneh it. ואי לא
לא, Ve-ilo lo, but if we don't pay you a fee, you'll
be קונה koneh it for yourself and it won't be a קרבן
ציבור. korban tzibbur. רבי יוסי סבר, Rabbi Yose savar, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose will say הבטה בהפקר לא קני, Abbata be-hefker lo kani, it
doesn't work. וכי אתו ציבור ומצרי, Ve-ki asai tzibbur u-mazri, השתא הוא
דקזכי ביה. hashta hu de-ka-zakhi beh. And when the ציבור tzibbur comes,
you've been watching it but you don't own it yet. You've just
been watching it. You've been watching it for free. We come, we
we harvest the wheat. It's now ours. Okay, and no problem. It's
a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. ומה אתה אומר, U-mah atah omer, and
what does it mean according to you? הכי קאמר להו, Haki ka-amar
kamilie, מדבריך לדברינו אין עומר ושתי הלחם באין משל ציבור. midvarecha lidvareinu
ein omer ushtei ha-lechem ba'in mishel tzibbur. Not according to you it's
not communal, but if if we were to take your פסק psak
that you don't pay the guy and apply it to our way
of thinking that הבטה Abbata is קונה, koneh, then it wouldn't be
a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. Within your way of thinking of course
it is, but your your פסק psak for us would make it
a non-קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. Okay, so here they're debating whether הבטה
Abbata would be קונה koneh or not. All right. Now,
by the way, here רש"י Rashi says, if you look about fifteen
lines, fifteen, I understand, fifteen lines from the bottom, the line starts
with the word בהפקר be-hefker in רש"י, Rashi, right near where it
says לעיל ע"ו עמוד א', la'el ayin-vav amud aleph, רש"י Rashi says
he explains why הבטה Abbata would be הפקר. hefker. הבטה תני בהפקר
הואיל ודבר טורח הוא ודעתו לכך על ידו נשמר. Abbata tanyi be-hefker
ho'il ve-davar torach hu ve-da'ato lakach al yado nishmar. So since it's
effort and you're protecting it and guarding it, that is exerting a
certain type of ownership over it. Okay. Anyway, so that's the debate.
It's really main it's being שומר הפקר קונה shomer hefker koneh is
really the issue. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ואי לא לא ורבי יוסי, ve-ilo lo ve-Rabbi Yose, affan where
were we? ומה U-mah okay, השתא הוא דקזכי
ביה. hashta hu de-ka-zakhi beh. ומה אתה אומר כן, U-mah atah omer
ken, הכי קאמר להו, haki ka-amar kamilie, מדבריך לדברינו אין עומר ושתי
הלחם באין משל ציבור. midvarecha lidvareinu ein omer ushtei ha-lechem ba'in mishel
tzibbur. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא, lo, דכולי עלמא הבטה בהפקר קני.
de-khuli alma Abbata be-hefker kani. Everybody would say it would work. Okay.
וסו Ve-so therefore what's the issue? I mean then it should be
a problem, the worker then is taking private possession.
והכא Ve-hacha so הכא חיישינן שמא
לא ימסור יפה יפה קמיפלגי.
hacha cheishinan shema lo
yimsur yafeh yafeh ka-miflagi.
The debate is everybody agrees the worker if you he wouldn't pay
him would own it. So why is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose okay
with it? Because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose figures fine, he owns it,
but then he'll fully donate it to the ציבור. tzibbur. He's not
going to make it his private קרבן korban and it's okay, let
him own it and then let him donate it. Okay.
ורבנן סברי יהבינן ליה אגרא, Ve-Rabbanan savri yahivin leh agra, we pay
him a fee, so therefore he doesn't own it. So if he's
watching it, he's watching it for us. ואי לא Ve-ilo and if
not, if he watches it for himself and he's קונה koneh it,
חיישינן שלא ימסור יפה יפה, cheishinan shelo yimsur yafeh yafeh, then we're
afraid that when he gives it to us, he he really wants
it to be his private קרבן עומר. korban Omer. He doesn't really
want it to be
a
ציבור. tzibbur. And what do they mean according to you? הכי קאמר
ליה, hachi ka’amar lei, same point. לדבריך לדברינו, le-devarecha le-devareinu, according to
you that say not to pay him, if we would apply that
within our construct that we're afraid then that people don't give a
full-hearted donation, דחיישינן שלא ימסור יפה יפה, de-hashinan she-lo yimsar yafe yafe,
אינו משלכם אלא משל ציבור, eino mi-shelachem ella mi-shel tzibur, then it
would not really be a full communal קרבן. korban. Okay. איכא דאמרי,
ika de-amri, some say, רב אמר הבטה בהפקר לא קני, Rav amar
habata be-hefker lo kani, okay, that it's not קונה. koneh. So if
it's not קונה, koneh, what do, why, why do we feel we
have to pay the guy? He wouldn't own it regardless. Okay, so
הכא דחיישינן לבעלי זרוע קמיפלגי. hacha de-hashinan le-va’alei zeroa kamiflagi. The question
is, we pay the guy not to make sure we own the
wheat in the end, but to scare off other people. If people
hear the bullies, if people hear that this guy is being paid
by the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they know it's בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash wheat and they're not going to try to force their way
to take the
wheat, okay? דתנא קמא סבר דתקינו רבנן למיתב ליה ארבע זוזי כי
היכי דלישמעו בעלי זרוע, de-tanna kamma savar de-takinu rabbanan le-meitav lei arba
zuzei ki heichi de-lishme’u ba’alei zeroa, we pay him even though of
course he wouldn't own the wheat regardless, we pay him in order
that it becomes public and the other, the forceful people get scared
off. Why ארבע זוזי? arba zuzei? I don't know, that's whatever. וליפרשו
מיניה, ve-lifreshu minei, and they'll separate. רבי יוסי סבר לא תקינו, Rebbi
Yose savar lo takinu, that we don't. ומה אתה אומר, ve-ma ata
omer, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka’amar lei. This is what they're saying.
לדבריך לדברינו, le-devarecha le-devareinu, according to you that we don't pay him.
So רש"י Rashi makes this very strange. We had the money assigned
to pay the guy and you're telling us that the guy says,
"Forget it, I'm מוחל, mochel, keep the money." So we're not keeping
the twenty bucks or whatever we would have paid him, we, you
know, he says, "I'm not going to take it, I'll watch for
free." So now twenty bucks of the Temple treasury will basically be
private money that was redonated back, okay? אינו בא משל ציבור, eino
ba mi-shel tzibur, then all the קרבנות korbanot we'll buy from that
twenty bucks won't be קרבן ציבור korban tzibur because that'll be the
stuff the guy gave back, which is a strange idea. What, like
just because I מוחל mochel that means that that's my money and
it's my private money? If I'm giving money to the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, it's now money of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. It's
very strange what the problem would be. Anyway, וכן כי אתא רבין
אמר רבי יוחנן חיישינן לבעלי זרוע איכא בינייהו. ve-chen ki ata Ravin
amar Rabbi Yochanan hashinan le-va’alei zeroa ika beineiyahu. The question is about
whether we have to pay the guy in order to scare off
other people, which makes it much more of a question why that
means that the קרבן korban would not be a קרבן ציבור. korban
tzibur. But anyway, going back to our case, what it means is
the question about whether you have to pay the guy or not
pay the guy, whether you can pay the guy in the straw
or not,
is according to the read that הבטה בהפקר לא קני. habata be-hefker
lo kani. If all he was doing was doing הבטה, habata, then
he wouldn't be קונה koneh the grain and therefore he would be
able to keep it for himself. So we understand why he could
keep it for himself, what we don't understand is why you wouldn't
have to pay him the fee that you arranged upon, but that
remains a question. Anyway, to me the more interesting that emerges from
all of this is the point that I said before, that you
don't necessarily always have to pay somebody based on a contract that
you've made according to the גמרא. Gemara. It seems it has to
work within a construct of שכירות skhirut and not everything is defined
as שכירות. skhirut. Okay, let's,
yes, Rabbi Dov. It looks like we are not going to finish
today. Yes, go ahead, it's okay. That's all right, we have tomorrow,
okay? I was just trying to get ahead.
Just re-explain in the first גמרא במאי קמיפלגי רבי יוסי סבר הבטה
בהפקר לא קני. Gemara be-mai kamiflagi Rebbi Yose savar habata be-hefker lo
kani. Right. כי אגרי ליה בבי מקמי דהשתא הוא דקזכי ביה, ki
agri lei be-bei mikamei de-hashta hu de-kazchi bei, but he זוכה? zocheh?
Not he זוכה, zocheh, the ציבור tzibur is זוכה. zocheh. Ah, okay.
You haven't been זוכה, zocheh, so now we're going to take it,
we're going to be זוכה. zocheh. Okay. המוציא זבלו לרשות הרבים. ha-motzi
zivlo le-reshut ha-rabim. Now, this is also things that were quoted in
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, okay? If somebody brought out, or these ideas,
somebody brings out their dung into רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, basically what
we're doing is I'm selling you my animal's dung and you're buying
it as fertilizer, so we're having our transaction in רשות הרבים. reshut
ha-rabim. So המוציא מוציא והמזבל מזבל. ha-motzi motzi ve-ha-mezabbel mezabbel. I bring
it out and as soon as I bring it out, you load
it up and you take it away and you bring and you,
you know, you bring it to where you're fertilizing. But basically, don't
leave my dung sitting in the middle of רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim
because as we'll discuss in the גמרא, Gemara, then if somebody slips
on it and gets hurt, I would be liable. So we have
to arrange it. On the one hand, רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim clearly
was not just a place of, you know, there are two types
of a רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, right? There's a סטרטיא stratiya and
a פלטיא. platya. A סטרטיא stratiya is like a road and a
פלטיא platya is a, like a square, right? And like you were
just in Israel recently, you know, with the family, right? You know,
I mean, along the walls of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and
along the, you know, outside the, you know, the Western Wall and
you know, the Cardo and all those things, these main roads, you
would obviously have it all lined with stores. Okay, so רשות הרבים
reshut ha-rabim was also a major place in which business was done.
So therefore, we're going to do our trading in the middle of
רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, but I can't leave my stuff out there,
you know, in a way that people are going to get damaged.
So we have to arrange it in a way where you're going
to come pick it up right away. So apparently I can't have
a big dung store with a big pile of dung waiting for
people to come buy it, okay? Because that's going to cause too
much damage and smell, or whatever in רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. I
made up the smell part. Okay. אין שורין טיט ברשות הרבים, ein
shurin tit be-reshut ha-rabim, similarly I can't go ahead and be making
my plaster in the middle of רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim. ואין לובנין
לבנים, ve-ein lovnin leveinim, and I can't go ahead and make bricks.
רש"י *Rashi* actually describes the way that you would make bricks is
that
you would basically take your plaster, whatever it is you'd make the
bricks with, your cement, lay it flat,
make the lines, the cross, based on the forms of the bricks.
Imagine you make a big flat thing of cement, right, and then
you draw the lines this way and that way, and then after
it hardens you have all those bricks out of it. You can't
do that in רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim, *Reshus Harabim*. Okay, you get
the public thoroughfare there's certain things you're allowed to do, other things
you have to go find some rent some field to do it
or do it in your own field. You can't do that in
רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim, *Reshus Harabim* presumably also because people will get
hurt, they'll step on it, they'll slip, they'll, whatever. אבל גובלין טיט
ברשות הרבים *Aval govlin tit bereshus harabim*. But what you can do
is you can knead it in רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*. Presumably maybe
because then you're actively involved in it, you're sitting over it, people,
you're not leaving it there alone, unattended.
It's convenient for me, why should I have to go out of
my way to,
but it's not out of your way. You have to understand that
a רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim* is not only a thoroughfare but a
public square where it's understood that people can do various things there.
Imagine a huge marketplace, right.
But you can't just take up a whole road.
Yeah, I mean, we're not talking about in the middle of the
road, right. Imagine that we're talking about a big marketplace and I'm
sitting in the marketplace and I'm both selling
my rugs and I'm also, have a little group of here that
are weaving the rugs as we're selling them, right. So, people were
doing these activities. It's interesting, it gives you a sense of what's
happening, right. But we have to have limits. You can't go ahead
and do all your stuff, stuff that's actually, so
why can't you soak the clay then?
I imagine because you're going to leave it unattended and that people
will slip and hurt themselves or whatever.
But if someone's over it then it would be fine? Is that
what you're saying? It's just מציאות *metzius* of whether someone's over it
or not? Then that's not really a function of what you're doing
then and the רשות *reshus* itself. According to your explanation,
there's two stages.
You're not allowed to do things that are public hazards, and then
there's a second question, which is are you liable if somebody gets
hurt? There's two separate questions. It starts with not doing things that
could create public hazards. Okay. So let's keep looking. הבונה ברשות הרבים
*Haboneh bereshus harabim*.
Now let's say you are doing a construction in רשות הרבים *Reshus
Harabim*. You've been hired by the רבים *rabim* to make some construction,
to build up some wall or something. Okay. How do you move
in the equipment in a way also that doesn't compromise the רבים
*rabim*? הבונה ברשות הרבים המביא אבנים מביא והבונה בונה *Haboneh bereshus harabim
hameivi avanim meivi vehaboneh boneh*. So similarly you can't have a guy
leave a huge pile of bricks and whatever and mortar because you're
working on some construction thing. You have to arrange it in a
way in which it's some type of an efficient
transition, even though you're working in רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*, right. So
he has to lay the bricks and he has to pile up
the bricks just as your workers are starting to lay them. You
can't leave these big mounds of construction material in the middle of
רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*. ואם הזיק משלם מה שהזיק *Ve-im hizik meshalem
mah she-hizik*. And if somebody is damaged as a result, you're liable.
Now that sounds like even if you were operating within the rules,
you have liability. And that's an important question we discussed in בבא
קמא *Bava Kama*. That it could be that as I was saying
a minute ago to Michael, there are two things. One is what
are you allowed and not allowed to do? And it could be
that even things you're allowed to do you have to assume liability.
But there are things that you're not allowed to do regardless of
whether you're willing to pay because they're too much of a hazard.
But even things that aren't, that we allow you to do, that
doesn't mean we free you from liability. רבן גמליאל אומר אף מתקנים
את מלאכתן לפני שלושים יום *Rabban Gamliel omer af metaknin es melachtan
lifnei shloshim yom*. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says no actually not, you
actually have 30 days if you're doing some construction in רשות הרבים
*Reshus Harabim*. You actually have 30 days beforehand to arrange the whole
worksite and to get the materials there, etc. And it's not clear
if he's just saying I'm allowed לכתחילה *l'chatchila* or is he also
saying I'm exempt from liability. So that difference of what you're allowed
and what you're liable for is not explicit in the משנה Mishna
*Mishna*. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. לימא מתניתין
דלא כרבי יהודה *Leima matnisin dela ke-Rebbi Yehuda*. Let's say our משנה
Mishna, *Mishna* is not like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda*. דתניא
*De-tanya*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* אומר *omer* בשעת הוצאת זבלים
אדם מוציא זבלו לרשות הרבים וצוברו כל שלושים יום *be-shat hotza'as zevelim
adam motzi zivlo lereshus harabim ve-tzovro kol shloshim yom*. There again, by
the way, notice the שלושים יום *shloshim yom* here we mentioned before,
דתנן בסיפא שלושים יום *de-tnan be-sifa shloshim yom*, שרבן גמליאל *she-Rabban Gamliel*
says you have 30 days to set up the site. Here רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* says you have 30 days to do
it at the time when people bring out their excrement, whatever, in
order to turn it into a fertilizer. So you can pile it
up in רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim* for 30 days כדי שישוף ברגלי
אדם וברגלי בהמה *kedei she-yishof beraglei adam u-veraglei beheima*. In order that
people trample on it and that somehow makes it better fertilizer. שעל
מנת כן הנחילו יהושע לישראל את הארץ *She-al menat kein hinchilu Yehoshua
le-Yisrael es ha-aretz*. That was one of the stipulations of inheriting the
land of Israel or of dividing the land of Israel. So it
sounds like he says it's allowed. If it's allowed, why would the
משנה Mishna *Mishna* have to say that you have to remove it
as soon as you brought it out? It sounds as if he
sounds like you're totally allowed לכתחילה *l'chatchila* to do it and to
leave it for 30 days and our משנה Mishna *Mishna* sounds like
you have to remove it immediately. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
no. אפילו תימא רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Afilu teima Rebbi Yehuda*. Even
could be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda*. מודה רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda שאם הזיק חייב לשלם *Modeh Rebbi Yehuda she-im hizik chayav l'shalem*.
No, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda* would say while you
have a right to do it, you would be liable. So when
our משנה Mishna *Mishna* says you have to remove it right away,
our משנה *Mishna*, again, it's always a little vague. And now the
גמרא's reading the משנה at least the first line like Michael wanted.
You don't have to remove it right away. You could actually leave
it there for 30 days. Okay, so in terms of what you're
allowed to do, you could leave it for 30 days. But if
you don't want to be free of liability, you'd better remove it
right away because if something happens in those 30 days, even though
you're allowed, you're still going to have to pay. Okay, so that
becomes the question of a difference between being allowed and being free
from liability. So the גמרא says, one minute, תנן, tenan, we taught
in the משנה, מודה רבי יהודה בנר חנוכה שהוא פטור, modeh Rabbi
Yehuda b'ner Chanukah shehu patur, that if you have your נר חנוכה
ner Chanukah out in your doorway and the camel with flax walks
by, you're exempt. Why? Because you were doing it, you had permission.
So presumably, at least according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who we're
talking like now, if you have permission, you're exempt from liability. מפני
שהוא עושה ברשות, mipnei shehu oseh birshut, because you did it with
permission. מאי לאו רשות דבית דין? mai lav rishut de-veit din? Don't
you see that once you have any type of legal right to
do it, you are exempt from liability? לא, רשות דמצוה. lo, rishut
de-mitzvah. No, maybe that's special because you were doing a מצוה. mitzvah.
But maybe if you had a legal right and it wasn't a
מצוה, mitzvah, you could still be liable. One minute, והתניא, ve-hatanya, don't
we teach in a ברייתא, brayta, כל אלו שאמרו מותרין לקלקל ברשות
הרבים, kol elu she-amru mutarin lekalkel bi-reshut ha-rabim, the people we allow
to make a mess in רשות הרבים, like to empty out their
waste products or whatever, and the rainwater? Nevertheless, even though you have
a right to do it, אם הזיק חייב לשלם, im hezik chayav
leshalem, you're still liable. That's the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, that you
can be permitted to do it and still be liable. But רבי
יהודה פוטר. poter. רבי יהודה says once you're allowed, then you're exempt.
So רבי יהודה both gives you more latitude to bring your excrement
into רשות הרבים, he lets you bring it there for 30 days,
and he says when you're allowed to do it, you're exempt from
liability. So our משנה says you gotta remove it right away, that
can't be רבי יהודה. רבי יהודה would let you have it 30
days and he would even say you wouldn't be liable. אלא, ella,
says the גמרא, מחוורתא מתניתין דלא כרבי יהודה. mechvarta matnitin d'lo ke-Rabbi
Yehuda.
You're right, our משנה is better not like רבי יהודה. Our משנה
presumably is that it says that presumably A, you're not allowed to
do it, or B, even if you are allowed to have it
longer, you would still be liable, whereas רבי יהודה allows you for
30 days and says you're free of liability. All right, let's read,
you know, I guess we'll end here so we have something to
do tomorrow.
Okay, we'll end here.